export const GEOGRAPHYA2009 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. What is the bearing Uwias from Sinavas?",
A: "45°",
B: "49°",
C: "110o",
D: "125o",
answer: "D. 125o",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. OKOMA is a good example of a",
A: "Gap town",
B: "Mining town",
C: "Port town",
D: "Coastal town",
answer: "A. Gap town",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. The vertical interval of the contour lines on the map is",
A: "100m",
B: "150m",
C: "200m",
D: "250m",
answer: "A. 100m",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The highest point in the area covered by the map is",
A: "900m",
B: "1100m",
C: "1500m",
D: "2000m",
answer: "B. 1100m",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. OKOMA is important because it is",
A: "An agricultural centre",
B: "An administrative centre",
C: "A road terminus",
D: "A gap town",
answer: "C. A road terminus",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Which of the following best describes the relief in the eastern part f the map?",
A: "Has a deep valley",
B: "Has a conical hill with the highest point in the area",
C: "Is a plain with the lowest point",
D: "Is dissected by numerous rivers",
answer: "B. Has a conical hill with the highest point in the area",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The area south of River Feyi lacks good communication network because",
A: "Economic activities are not likely to be practiced in the area",
B: "Riverine areas do not normally need good communication network",
C: "The area south of River Feyi is liable to flooding",
D: "People in the area do not travel much by land.",
answer: "C. The area south of River Feyi is liable to flooding",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. The major factor that influenced the settlement pattern in the map is",
A: "Relief",
B: "Drainage",
C: "Mineral resources",
D: "Plantation agriculture",
answer: "A. Relief",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Sinavas is a good location for",
A: "Cement factory",
B: "Shoe factory",
C: "Palm oil processing factory",
D: "Iron smelting factory",
answer: "C. Palm oil processing factory",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. What is the drainage pattern of River Feyi and its tributaries?",
A: "Centrifugal",
B: "Radial",
C: "Trellis",
D: "Dendritic",
answer: "D. Dendritic",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. The largest planet in the solar system is",
A: "Mars",
B: "Jupiter",
C: "Venus",
D: "Earth",
answer: "B. Jupiter",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. The greatest contrast between the planets Mercury and Jupiter is in their",
A: "Direction of orbit",
B: "Inhabitability",
C: "Size",
D: "Shape",
answer: "C. Size",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. The inclination of the earth’s axis at the angle of 66½o results in",
A: "The lunar eclipse",
B: "Different seasons and varying length of day and night",
C: "The eclipse of the sun",
D: "The rise and fall of tides",
answer: "B. Different seasons and varying length of day and night",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The sun is normally overhead at the equator",
A: "March 21 and December 22",
B: "March 21 and December 22",
C: "June 21 and December 22",
D: "December 22 and September 23",
answer: "B. March 21 and December 22",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. When it is 11am in London, longitude 0°, what is the local time in town X on longitude 75°W?",
A: "4:00 am",
B: "6:00am",
C: "4:00 pm",
D: "6:00 pm",
answer: "B. 6:00am",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. In the diagram above, the areas A and B receive an equal amount o solar energy but area A has higher temperature because  \nI. The sun’s rays meet area B at an oblique angle and spread over a larger area than A  \nII. Area B lies in the southern hemisphere  \nIII. The sun’s rays at B pass through a greater thickness of atmosphere than at B  \nIV. Area B has a thicker landmass than A",
A: "I and III only",
B: "I, II and III only",
C: "II and IV only",
D: "II only",
answer: "A. I and III only",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. The earth’s crust is made up of",
A: "Sial and sima",
B: "Sima and nife",
C: "Nifeandsial",
D: "Sima and alumina",
answer: "A. Sial and sima",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. Small crystals of rock formed from lava which have solidified rapidly on the earth’s surface are referred to as",
A: "Metamorphic rocks",
B: "Volcanic rocks",
C: "Plutonic rocks",
D: "Gneiss",
answer: "B. Volcanic rocks",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. Which of the following is an example of a volcanic mountain?",
A: "The Atlas Mountains",
B: "Mount Kilimanjaro",
C: "The Rocky Mountains",
D: "The Andes Mountains",
answer: "B. Mount Kilimanjaro",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. Mountains formed by molten lava ejected onto the earth’s surface are called",
A: "Fold mountains",
B: "Rocky mountains",
C: "Block mountains",
D: "Volcanic mountains",
answer: "D. Volcanic mountains",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Which of the following is not a process of soil formation?",
A: "Rock weathering",
B: "Leaching",
C: "Eluviation",
D: "Conservation",
answer: "A. Rock weathering",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Which of the following is not a process of soil formation?",
A: "Rock weathering",
B: "Leaching",
C: "Eluviation",
D: "Conservation",
answer: "D. Conservation",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. Which of the Following factors favour delta formation?",
A: "Large lakes in the course of river",
B: "Deep sea adjoining the river mouth",
C: "Active erosion in the upper course of a river.",
D: "Strong current running at right angles to the river mouth",
answer: "B. Deep sea adjoining the river mouth",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The salinity of the sea refers to the",
A: "Volume of water in the sea",
B: "Volume of mud deposited by rivers",
C: "Amount of salt in the sea",
D: "Usefulness of the sea to people",
answer: "C. Amount of salt in the sea",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. All the following are warm ocean currents except",
A: "Guinea Current Counter",
B: "Canary Current",
C: "Mozambique Current",
D: "Brazilian Current",
answer: "B. Canary Current",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Which of the following seas has the highest salinity?",
A: "The white sea",
B: "The Caspian sea",
C: "The Black sea",
D: "The Dead sea",
answer: "D. The Dead sea",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. Which of the following does not influence marine erosion?",
A: "Ocean current",
B: "Salinity of the ocean",
C: "Nature of the coastline",
D: "Strength of the waves",
answer: "B. Salinity of the ocean",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The arrow head on wind vanes points in the direction",
A: "Of the north",
B: "Of the magnetic north pole",
C: "From which the wind is blowing",
D: "Of the south pole",
answer: "C. From which the wind is blowing",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. The zone of the atmosphere where changes in weather conditions take place is the",
A: "Mesosphere",
B: "Ionosphere",
C: "Troposphere",
D: "Tropopause",
answer: "C. Troposphere",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. The instrument use to measure relative humidity is",
A: "Hygrometer",
B: "Barometer",
C: "Anemometer",
D: "Thermometer",
answer: "A. Hygrometer",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Lines joining places of equal salinity of the oceans are known as",
A: "lsonephs",
B: "Isothermns",
C: "Isolialine",
D: "Isobars",
answer: "C. Isolialine",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. The annual range of temperature is",
A: "3°C",
B: "14°C",
C: "18°C",
D: "31°C",
answer: "A. 3°C",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. What is the total annual rainfall?",
A: "125mm",
B: "185mm",
C: "226mm",
D: "473mm",
answer: "D. 473mm",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. The most predominant action in the first horizon of a soil profile is",
A: "Sedimentation",
B: "Eluviation",
C: "Saturation",
D: "Illuviation",
answer: "B. Eluviation",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. Soil erosion often results from",
A: "Man’s indiscriminate clearing of the vegetation",
B: "Controlled grazing",
C: "Cultivation across slopes",
D: "Exfoliation",
answer: "A. Man’s indiscriminate clearing of the vegetation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. The trees are evergreen with interlocking canopies and huge buttress roots. This is a description of the trees found in",
A: "Equatorial forest",
B: "Guinea savanna",
C: "Mediterranean woodland",
D: "Sudan savanna",
answer: "A. Equatorial forest",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. The Grand Banks of Newfoundland are valuable to man because they provide",
A: "Game reserve for tourists",
B: "Good harbours",
C: "Good fishing grounds",
D: "Petroleum",
answer: "C. Good fishing grounds",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Which of the following resources is renewable?",
A: "Petroleum",
B: "Peat",
C: "Lignite",
D: "Hydroelectricity",
answer: "B. Peat",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Temperate grassland are best developed",
A: "On the western sides of continents",
B: "In the continental interiors of temperate latitudes",
C: "On the east of continents",
D: "Between latitude 0o and 20o",
answer: "B. In the continental interiors of temperate latitudes",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. All the following have resulted in the decline of death rates except",
A: "Improvement in hygiene and sanitation",
B: "Production of more foods",
C: "Improvement in medical sciences",
D: "The use of contraceptives",
answer: "D. The use of contraceptives",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. One major advantage of a high population density is",
A: "Large labour force",
B: "Large labour force",
C: "Large market",
D: "Small market",
answer: "B. Large labour force",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. A confluence town is a town where",
A: "Two or more rivers diverge",
B: "Two or more routes converge",
C: "Conflicts are common",
D: "Two or more rivers meet",
answer: "D. Two or more rivers meet",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Despite the rapid development in modern air transport, its service is still useful to only a small proportion of the world’s population because",
A: "Many countries do not have airlines",
B: "People fear air disasters",
C: "It cost more to travel by air",
D: "Other forms of transport are quicker",
answer: "C. It cost more to travel by air",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. The busiest air route in the world is the one between",
A: "Europe and Asia",
B: "Africa and the USA",
C: "Europe and North America",
D: "Asia and Africa",
answer: "C. Europe and North America",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. In which of the following areas would building of roads be most expansive?",
A: "Barren lands",
B: "Grassy lands",
C: "Dry lands",
D: "Swampy lands",
answer: "D. Swampy lands",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Which of the following cannot be obtained from the by-products of crude oil?",
A: "Plastic",
B: "Synthetic rubber",
C: "Glass",
D: "Insecticides",
answer: "C. Glass",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. Which of the following is the most industrially advanced country in Africa?",
A: "Nigeria",
B: "Egypt",
C: "South Africa",
D: "Zimbabwe",
answer: "C. South Africa",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. A major problem faced by most diamond producing countries in Africa is",
A: "The falling price for African diamonds in the world market",
B: "Low demand for diamond",
C: "The activities of illicit diamond smugglers",
D: "Fall in the value of African currencies to the US dollar",
answer: "A. The falling price for African diamonds in the world market",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. The Masai of East Africa are",
A: "Food gatherers",
B: "Nomadic pastoralists",
C: "Sedentary agriculturists",
D: "Mostly miners",
answer: "B. Nomadic pastoralists",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. Which of the following countries is a member of ECOWAS?",
A: "Chad Republic",
B: "Guinea Bissau",
C: "Botswana",
D: "Zimbabwe",
answer: "B. Guinea Bissau",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},


]